<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<pubdate>201201</pubdate>
				<title>Philadelphia Land Use</title>
				<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
				<onlink>http://www.pasda.psu.edu</onlink></citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>City of Philadelphia land use as ascribed to individual parcel boundaries or units of land.  Land use is the type of activity occurring on the land such as residential, commercial or industrial.  Each unit of land is assigned to one of nine major classifications of land use (2-digit codes) and where possible more narrowly defined into one of 70 sub-classifications (3-digit codes).  

AS OF JUNE 2011 this land use feature class was field checked and corrected for Planning Districts: West Park and Lower South.  Subsequent field checks and edits will occur as part of the Philadelpia2035 District Planning process through 2014.

Last edited   10/14/2011
Metadata updated:  10/18/2011</abstract>
			<purpose>Citywide land use as determined by the City Philadelphia Planning Commission (PCPC). Prepared for Philadelphia2035, the City’s comprehensive development plan, to support the zoning reform remapping and the District Planning projects. For more information on the Philadelphia2035 comprehensive planning process, see www.phila2035.org Land use classifications are activity-based. Each land unit has only one land use designation interpreted by a 1, 2 or 3-digit code. Specificity of a land use description increases from the one to three digit code. Example: 1= Residential, 1.2 = Residential Medium Density, and 1.2.1 = Residential Rowhouse.Land use features are derived from Philadelphia Water Department tax parcel boundaries (2009 to current release date) and from other GIS datasets prepared by City departments including: planimetric features, transportation right-of-ways (ROW), parks and open space, and water. Land use boundaries are typically coincident with PWD tax parcel boundaries, where tax parcel boundaries are available to define units of land. In some cases multiple land activities on a single parcel and been individual represented as individual polygons of land use. This land use feature class is under revision through 2014. Updates will be made to correct attributes and features and to populate 3-digit codes based upon field verifications made by PCPC staff. Land use field surveys will be conducted for each of the 18 Planning District beginning in 2011 as part of the Philadelphia2035 Compressive Planning process. For areas not yet updated by a Planning District field survey, land use designations are qualified estimates derived from the Office of Property Assessment data (see details under “Development Process” below). Landuse Codes and DescriptionsLanduse codes are organized from the 1-digit to 3-digit level. Specificity of land use increases with each increasing digit. Coded numeric values are stored as integers. Full text descriptions are contained in separate string fields. Values in the 3-digit code and description fields may not be fully populated, indicating that these features have not been field verified, or that this level of specificity cannot be accurately assigned. All features are attributed at the 1- and 2-digit levels.Key Attribute Fieldsc_Dig1 - 1-digit level land use coding, numeric code.c_Dig2 - 2-digit level land use coding, numeric code.c_Dig3 - 3-digit level land use coding, numeric code.c_Dig1Desc - 1-digit level land use text description.c_Dig2Desc - 2-digit level land use text description.c_Dig3Desc - 3-digit level land use text description.LU_Current - year land use features are current to. For "2010" records, land use values are NOT field checked and were derived as described above from available City database sources. Considred draft values.2-digit Codes and Descriptions1.0 Residential 1.1 Residential Low Density1.2 Residential Medium Density1.3 Residential High Density2.0 Commercial2.1 Commercial Consumer2.2 Commercial Business and Professional2.3 Commercial Mixed Residential 3.0 Industrial 4.0 Civic/Institution5.0 Transportation6.0 Culture/Recreation6.1 Culture/Amusement6.2 Active Recreation7.0 Park/Open Space7.1 Park/Open Space7.2 Cemetery8.0 Water9.0Vacant or Other9.1 Vacant Land9.2 Other/UnknownDevelopment ProcessThe PCPC acquired the Philadelphia Water Department's (PWD) tax parcel boundary feature class (2009) for use as base layer geometry. This parcel base does not contain transportation, park, or water features required for identification of land uses for every unit of land across the entire city. Separate feature classes were acquired by the PCPC to represent all other land features streets, highways and rail right of ways, rail yards, parks and open space, parking lots and sidewalks, and marine terminals. Multiple feature classes were merged into a single feature class in ArcGIS 9x to produce a seamless fabric of land and water features citywide. Gaps in the spatial fabric persisted where feature classes did not topologically align. Gaps, slivers and overlaps between features, resulting from the merge process, were identified and edited using ArcGIS geodatabase topology rules.The resulting draft “Land Use 2010” feature class was joined with the Office of Property Assessment (OPA), formerly BRT, real estate database (2009). The PCPC used OPA building description values from the real estate table as the basis for land use categorization. All features were attributed to the 2-digit level. PCPC staff checked and corrected these categorizations using the following resources: PhilaShops retail properties database (2003); Philadelphia Industrial Development Corporation’s Industrial Market and Landuse Strategy report (2009), and Philadelphia Parks and Recreation (PPR) parks land and facilities database (2010). Under the Philadelphia2035 District Planning process, this feature class will undergo field verification as each Planning District project is completed. A total of 18 Planning Districts will be surveyed from 2011 to 2015. Field verification results in corrections to land use attributes and population of the 3-digit land use codes, which cannot otherwise cannot be determined without field inspection. Revisions to this land use feature class will be posted as survey work and evaluation for each Planning District is fully completed. Thematic MappingFor thematic mapping, use the c_dig2 or c_Dig2Desc fields. The c_Dig2Desc field maintains the full text description of the 2-digit land use codes (e.g., 11 = Residential Low Density). An ESRI ArcGIS layer file (.lyr) with pre-set symbology is available from the PCPC. Symbol RGB Values11 - Residential Low : 255, 255, 20412 - Residential Medium : 245, 255, 1813 - Residential High : 255, 170, 021 - Commercial Consumer : 230, 0, 022 - Commercial Business/Professional : 168, 0, 023 -Mixed Commercial/Residential : 232, 149, 12131 - Industrial : 140, 0, 25541 - Civic/Institution: 0, 112, 25551 - Transportation : 204, 204, 20461 - Culture/Recreation : 0, 255, 23062 - Active Recreation: 155,204,179; 99, 204, 071 - Park/Open Space : 99, 204, 072 - Cemetery : 99, 204, 0; 107, 126, 14781 - Water : 191, 232, 25591 - Vacant: 168, 112, 092 - Other/Unknown: 107, 126, 174; 210, 210, 210</purpose>
		</descript>
		<status>
			<update>Annually</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-75.284167</westbc>
				<eastbc>-74.954039</eastbc>
				<northbc>40.143797</northbc>
				<southbc>39.861288</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords><theme><themekey>Land Use</themekey><themekey>Land Cover</themekey><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey></theme></keywords>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>Landuse is not a substitute for, or an equivalency to, zoning and is not a legal determination of property use or property boundaries.  Site specific verification may be required. Calculations of land use by category are approximations.  Gaps and misalignments between features are due to the import of spatial features produced by different City departments, and topological integrity among features is not present.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>City Philadelphia Planning Commission</cntorg>
					<cntper>Mark Wheeler</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Unknown</addrtype>
					<address>1515 Arch Street, One Parkway Building</address>
					<city>Philadelphia</city>
					<state>PA</state>
					<postal>19102</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>215-683-4686</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>mark.wheeler@phila.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>CONTACT:

Mark Wheeler, GISP
City Planner
City Philadelphia Planning Commission
1515 Arch Street, 13th Floor
Philadelphia PA 19102
mark.wheeler@phila.gov
215-683-4686
</datacred>
		<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcGIS 10.0.0.2414</native>
		<timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>201201</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd></idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<typesrc>None</typesrc>
				<srccontr>Philadelphia Water Department tax parcels 2009
Philadelphia Water Department impervious surfaces 2009
Philadelphia Parks and Recreation Department parks 2009 (formerly Fairmount Park Commission data).
Office of Property Assessmetn real estate table 2009 (formerly BRT)
</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<typesrc>None</typesrc>
				<srccontr>PWD Parcels 2009</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Vector</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>569928</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
		</ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<mapproj>
					<lambertc>
						<stdparll>39.93333333333333</stdparll>
						<stdparll>40.96666666666667</stdparll>
						<longcm>-77.75</longcm>
						<latprjo>39.33333333333334</latprjo>
						<feast>1968500.0</feast>
						<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
					</lambertc>
				</mapproj>
				<planci>
					<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>0.000000026907964745248598</absres>
						<ordres>0.000000026907964745248598</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu>Foot_US</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>Land_Use</enttypl>
			</enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig1</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig1Desc</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig2</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig2Desc</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig3</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>c_Dig3Desc</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>LU_CURRENT</attrlabl>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>SHAPE_AREA</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>SHAPE_LEN</attrlabl>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
	</eainfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>201201</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>Philadelphia City Planning Commission</cntorg>
					<cntper>Mark Wheeler</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Planner</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Unknown</addrtype>
					<address>1515 Arch Street, One Parkway Bldg</address>
					<city>Philadelphia</city>
					<state>PA</state>
					<postal>19102</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntemail>mark.wheeler@phila.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
		<metuc>Landuse is not a substitute for, or an equivalency to, zoning and is not a legal determination of property use.  Site specific verification may be required. </metuc>
	</metainfo>
	<distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Pennsylvania Spatial Data Access (PASDA) </cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>115 Land and Water Building</address><city>University Park</city><state>Pennsylvania</state><postal>16802</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>(814) 865 8792</cntvoice><cntemail>pasda@psu.edu </cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>The USER shall indemnify, save harmless, and, if requested, defend those parties involved with the development and distribution of this data, their officers, agents, and employees from and against any suits, claims, or actions for injury, death, or property damage arising out of the use of or any defect in the FILES or any accompanying documentation. Those parties involved with the development and distribution excluded any and all implied warranties, including warranties or merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose and makes no warranty or representation, either express or implied, with respect to the FILES or accompanying documentation, including its quality, performance, merchantability, or fitness for a particular purpose. The FILES and documentation are provided "as is" and the USER assumes the entire risk as to its quality and performance. Those parties involved with the development and distribution of this data will not be liable for any direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages arising out of the use or inability to use the FILES or any accompanying documentation.</distliab></distinfo></metadata>
